it's a February 24th 2020 and my guest
is junk
karaoke John is a CIA whistleblower or
was oh hang on let's just change my view
I'm recording on his Omega was I should
say and is now a successful author and a
radio show host hello John hello thanks
for having me
yeah thanks for being back so I asked
you to comment on the expedition
hearings I shouldn't say trial trial I
think my hearings over of Julian Assange
so let's dig into that what's your take
on what's happening here in London I'm
in London by the way so just sure so
you're in London okay good um well day
one this is a long process there it's a
very long process actually it's gonna
stretch into July by all accounts and
there's gonna be a break of at least a
month in the midst of this thing at the
request of the American prosecutors just
because they say they can't remain in
London for such a long stretch they're
gonna have to come back here and regroup
I find that to be very odd but I do
think that that the fact that it's
scheduled for such a long period of time
is a good thing for Julian because it's
going to give the defence
I think ample opportunity to get a lot
of facts into the record about the
American prison system that otherwise
would have been overlooked or ignored I
think that's a good thing well what
would be the top number one fact about
the American prison system that they
need meat in them well it's what Neal's
Melser has been saying the special the
UN special record tour for for torture
that the u.s. practice of solitary
confinement meets the definition of
torture at the United Nations and and
there's a precedent there are actually
several precedents in British
jurisprudence where prisoners have been
where the courts have refused to
extradite British prisoners to the
United States because they would be
subjected to solitary confinement so
fingers crossed I was I was not in the
courtroom I don't hold a press card so I
can't be journalists inside so I was
outside with the people protesting and
well there was some Brits there were
some people from London a Norwegian guy
Dennis got me from Holland and then the
French showed up yeah I heard it was
like a hundred of 50 well we call them
the yellow vests and they they're the
heroes of the day days but they arrived
in Oh somewhere in the morning and they
did stop singing until the court was
surface
recessed and banging defenses and
everything and that was weird
heard also in in the courtrooms now I
just finished talking to a member of
European Parliament market a Geiger OVA
as he's here as an observer and he said
well there weren't seats reserved for me
as a European Parliament member but I
got in line and I and and I was one of
the first people in I didn't know where
to go so I asked when was she here the
guys and he said well yeah courtroom too
so she went there was empty set down and
as he stayed sitting there until the
room filled up as he was in there she
wasn't supposed to be the stories this
stories he told from the courtroom is
that the audio system was off so the
microphones weren't working so even
people in the room couldn't hear what
the judge was saying now Asajj was
sitting behind a plastic wall thingy so
he had trouble hearing his own courts
this mess that I just described is that
common in United States also no no it's
funny to me that they had him behind a
plexiglass shield the British do that
for some reason not all the time but
sometimes that's something that's just
unheard of in the United States and in
the u.s. even if the system even if the
power were out and I've never heard of
anything like that happening you're in
such close proximity to each other that
you can still hear what's going on the
handful of times that I've been in
courtrooms you didn't even really need a
microphone you're so close to one
another that you can hear everything but
you know this I have to say this doesn't
surprise me at all it sounds like more
of a circus sideshow than it does an
actual legal hearing yeah so so it's
it's amateurism if that's what you're
saying that's what it sounds like to me
you think they would have tested the
sound system at first on a case like
this earlier so the impression that I
got is and here's a little lead-up to a
more serious question you have the
French and me and the other guys
outside banging defenses cheering
cheering Freedom of Information cheering
the right for publishers to publish
right cheering let this our street so
that's this the one party in this and on
the other end you have the party that
wants him extradited
and in the middle there's the actual
courtroom with Asajj now I would I would
the word victim might be out of context
here but he's sitting in the middle
between those two parties with his legal
team up against the American prosecutors
and I'm a Christian to you is who in
United States wants him extradited end
of the line really the only the only
people the only organization that is
even talking about extradition is the US
Justice Department certainly there's no
movement among the American populace
demanding the head of Julian Assange I
said in an earlier interview that at
least 95 percent of Americans have never
heard of Julian Assange they don't
follow these issues they don't pay any
attention to the news or to the case
this is an act by the US Department of
Justice to try to prosecute a journalist
to try to prosecute a publisher and so
that's where that's the driving force
here it's not the American public
demanding that someone pay for example
for releasing classified information the
truth of the matter here Rico is that oh
did I lose you
there you are not for a second this the
truth of the matter is that that Julian
Assange blew the whistle on American war
crimes it is illegal in this country to
classify a crime if something is a crime
by definition it cannot be classified
and the American people have the right
to know what their what their government
is doing in their name Julian assigns
released that information that's a
public service it's not a crime so so
Justice Department is the Justice
Department and an extension of the
current administration in the White
House or is that disconnect it there
well in a way but in a way most of these
prosecutors are career prosecutors there
are the same people that were
prosecuting cases under Barack Obama and
under george w bush before him so i
don't think it's so much ideological as
it is institutional and and it's it's
the the professional prosecutors at the
justice department who are looking for
his scalp okay okay now what i
understand from the court documents is
that the
kriste is based solely on what's
happened in the Afghan locks Afghan war
logs and irregular war logs so the stuff
Chelsea Manning leaked beckoned and it
was published in 2010 so why wasn't the
later stuff included there do you think
like 47 what was also through WikiLeaks
yeah my guess is that they're holding
that information in reserve in case they
they do get him here and he is somehow
acquitted of the the leaks in the Afghan
and Iraq war logs they have that in
reserve to charge him with new crimes
afterwards it sounds like it's personal
I'm gonna ask you again who is the who's
the person is there a person that has a
personal issue with the Sarge or is it
an institutional personal thing yeah I
think it's I think it's institutional I
think it's the the Justice Department's
National Security Division I think it's
the prosecutors in the Eastern District
of Virginia and certainly the judges in
the Eastern District of Virginia and
then you had this this completely
gung-ho
Attorney General now former attorney
general in Jeff Sessions who got them
who got the wheels moving in the first
place William bar William bar is not
Jeff Sessions his job is to protect the
president as he sees it and putting
Julian Assange in prison I think is
going to help with with the Republican
base okay we'll talk about Republican
base there's a as seen from this side of
the Atlantic there's a disconnect
between the DNC and the Trump group it
just is so you say ninety five percent
of Americans may not have heard of the
asan story but is there a similar
disconnect between the other five
percent and the general population look
like really apart yeah there is there is
because there are a lot of Democrats who
blame Julian Assange personally for
giving us Donald Trump they believe that
that his release of the DNC
emails in the in the weeks before the
2016 election guaranteed Donald Trump's
victory and they just will not forgive
him for that yeah but did the previous
question URL so there was so it's
Justice Department it's not it's not the
DNC thing that that's involved in this
case right yes well the DNC doesn't have
the authority to do something but my
point really is that that you know
Democrats ought to be Julian Assange is
natural constituency here it should be
Democrats and progressives who are in
the streets demanding that Julian be
released and it's not it's not in this
case I mean those of us who are true
progressives yes we're the ones that in
the streets we're the ones marching to
the White House and marching to the
Justice Department
but run-of-the-mill Democrats no because
they blame him for Donald Trump okay so
what's what what's going on in
Washington today what's there in a
demonstration
yeah there's a demonstration right now
as we speak let me actually look to see
what time it is it's two o'clock so I'm
sorry it's evening
yes it's evening in London two hours ago
the demonstration began at the White
House it moved on to the Trump
International Hotel and from there it
went just another couple blocks down the
street to the Department of Justice to
the attorney general's office they're
gonna continue doing that every day this
week just to keep up the pressure and
it's a variety of progressive groups and
transparency groups okay yeah which I
identify as Democrats then or is that
know talked about yeah no actually I
know all of the speakers and and no they
don't identify as Democrats they
identify as either independence or
greens because they believe like I do
that the Democratic Party is so similar
to and consistent with the Republican
Party that there's really not much of a
difference between the two people are
thinking that's gonna might even split
even after these elections you say I
would not be surprised by that at all
and on the other side note you see
Clinton coming into the game again or no
you
against her you know I I loathe Hillary
Clinton I think Hillary Clinton was one
of those dangerous political figures of
the last generation but the rumor is
that she might agree to be vice
president under Mike Bloomberg we just
have to keep our fingers crossed that we
don't trade one corrupt billionaire for
another corrupt billionaire and you know
I for one am I love Bernie Sanders I'm
going to proudly vote for Bernie Sanders
in two weeks and it looks like he has
enough momentum to put everybody else
away but that's not to say that the
Democratic National Committee won't
steal this thing from him at the
Democratic convention again exactly
as an aside looking back at 2016 Bernie
Sanders won the the West Virginia
primary and the Colorado caucus won
handily and didn't get a single delegate
in either one of those states Hillary
Clinton got all the delegates that's not
democracy that's theft and we're afraid
of happening again exactly does will be
my prediction so as seen from this side
of the Atlantic that's happen again and
that's gonna breed a breakup of
Democratic Party yeah and Trump's gonna
win anyway another question I just told
you I'm gonna talk to ya well it's in
the future so I hope it's gonna pull
through but I'm about to talk to John
McAfee yes all right so he's the guy to
the event it's one of the first
antivirus products now he claims there
no such thing as computer privacy or
encryption everything that works will
have has been compromised oh I believe
he's taken a different approach then at
Snowden who says well if you do properly
encryption works what's your take on
that well I'm not a computer expert but
I've been in touch with that Snowden and
Bill Binney and Tom Drake and Kirk Wiebe
and guys who are computer experts and
they tell me that if the encryption is
sophisticated enough if the key is
sophisticated enough that it can work
the danger though is that it's
intercepted before you encrypt it so if
so if NSA for example is spying on you
or the FBI or CIA are spying on you and
they're able to target your computer as
you're typing your message before you
hit the encryption key then they've got
you yeah and so it's it's far less safe
and far less reliable than most people
realize I think so only a week or two
weeks ago by now in the news was that a
Swiss company crypto AG right you've got
that story oh yes so yeah I'm asking a
former CIA employee but it was did you
know about that back in the day was this
common no no no no this was highly
classified highly compartmentalized you
know I was in a senior position of the
CIA and I I had no idea I gave an
interview about this last week to a
Russian Network and it was really one of
the funniest interviews I've ever given
and I didn't mean for it to be funny but
this woman was asking me very loaded
questions like is anybody going to be
prosecuted for this and I said no but I
think several people will probably win
medals for it there's there's a wildly
successful operation it's not viewed as
a crime it's you it's viewed as
something heroic and patriotic and she
said but it's it's not honest to do
something like this and I said no it's
it's intelligence it's an intelligence
operation it's not supposed to be honest
it's not supposed to be fair it's not
supposed to make for a level playing
field this is something that
intelligence services do all around the
world yeah but still it is supposed to
be in a general public interest on to
Arnold I mean there's
yummy I mean why else are we spending
like it wrong why else are we spending
our tax money all the time well this is
in the public interest it's in the US
public interest for the CIA to crack the
codes of every other country in the
world very much in the public interest
yes I'm here
the reason that I'm here is this like
like soul searching searching for the
soul and United Kingdom in London and be
activists here who shows up into
journalists who show up politicians and
and to see if Asajj has any chance at
all on a fair trial and then the
microphones don't work should they want
and the microphones don't work yeah so
you know one thing I'm worried about too
is let's say Julian let's say that the
judge denies the US government's request
to extradite Julian that's going to be
seen as a huge victory but then what
happens Julian is an Australian citizen
he just recently in the last year or so
had his Australian passport renewed so
he has a current passport if he's then
expelled from the United Kingdom and
sent to Australia the US will just ask
the Australians to extradite him it
would be so much better if he were
allowed to leave for Russia or if there
were a country that would be willing to
brought provide him with asylum because
I don't think that he would be safe if
he wins and he's expelled to Australia
how I don't know do United Kingdom legal
system but if you don't get extradited
you don't get expelled do you I mean do
you do sure you do because he's not a
British citizen he doesn't have a right
to remain in Britain no doesn't he have
the right to choose his own plane on
which he leaves I would hope so that's
really the big question I would hope so
so here's an or say you know unless they
escort him to the airport and just put
him on the first plane to to Melbourne
Sydney France maybe I mean that would be
great
I heard he addressed asylum there yeah I
heard the same thing okay last question
that I have for you I prepared for you
you're aware you're familiar with a
software product called secure drop I
assume so I was not and I still don't
know did the workings of it exactly but
on a higher level if you're a
whistleblower you have some stuff that
you want to expose to media you would
volunteer it to your drop and that
mechanism would land it to the media
without there being connection between
me and the material that I'm leaking
right that's security yes okay yes and
if you go to various media outlets in
United States you go to the websites you
might find secure drop on there as one
of the means to to get the information
for them yes I got that right
and it was built among others Assange
was one of the people getting that
system working correct Aaron Swartz was
on there so these would be totally
independent people trying to get that
system to work okay my question is
there's not a product product as well
and that was global eeks that's also a
software product that was adopted maybe
among other parties but by a Dutch
organization pop leaks publics is using
the global leaks offer and does the same
thing and I just described have you
heard about publics before no there's
this is the first time I've heard of it
okay
well my question to you is if you find
the time and you know people I want to
know if I can how how I should weigh
publics as compared to secure drop Oh
most definitely bill Binney and and Tom
Drake give you a detailed answer on that
I will connect it wonderful better I'm
gonna connect to them
excellent okay oh yeah yeah before I
hang up on this phone in the Netherlands
we have a law it's called yeah in Dutch
house phone clock allowed us home of
whistleblowers now that law sounds
really great like some laws tend to do
so that's like a safe place built into
law where whistle blows can go so they
don't have to leak to the press how cool
is that
we don't need the Fourth Estate because
in that safe and secure house of his
Louis all things are and you get even
get a so kind of a whistleblower
certificates that you're a real one so
you're protected that rep I can form a
Secret Service person in a Netherlands
is on the on their board that kind of an
organization so they're about to
evaluate that law and how it frictions
and well it doesn't really function that
well my question break if you were to
build an NGO and if you would get a law
in that would fund that NGO through the
tax money let's let's let's just dream
that that would be reality someday who
would be the people deciding on who's on
the board of such NGO how would we get
an abort and an organization protecting
whistleblowers and their rights so that
it's not corrupted well actually such an
organization already exists it's called
blueprint for free speech it's based in
Australia and the board members are
mostly academics and some of them are
transparency and privacy activists I've
worked with them for years and they've
been able to write draft legislation
draft whistleblower protection
legislation and marketed around the
world so they hired me in 2015 to help
the Greek government write a new
whistleblower protection law we wrote it
in 2015 it was finally passed into law
in 2018 and then a version of it was
adopted by the European Parliament for
for implementation in the European Union
it's not perfect of course because it
had to go through so many different
layers of amendments and in writing and
rewriting and it had to be approved by
all the different countries but they've
had success in places like Canada and
Zambia and Jamaica and Ukraine pushing
this whistleblower protection
legislation it's it's hard work and it's
a very long and drawn-out process but it
actually works in the end in in most
places that are serious about that kind
of legislation well the United disunited
I was going to say to your P Union that
they're not so so United as they'd like
to be but European Union has a
whistleblower directive that thing is
supposed to be passed into law into
various Member States yes one of the
it's watered down right so that what's
really asking it also the restrictions
that does not apply to is Brussels
itself so nice it's like a Buddhist the
United States but not for Washington
that's kind of a whistle blow it was and
that and that's how every piece of
legislation is here Congress is
automatically exempt from coverage like
for example OSHA the Occupational Safety
and Health Act Congress doesn't have to
observe any of it they exempt themselves
from coverage same thing all over but
okay you were involved with the thing
from Australia and it definitely kind of
research into that yeah to your
knowledge were they involved in any way
with the Dutch a law or evaluation is
taking place now um I don't know but I
can tell you that the that the founder
and director of blueprint for free
speech is dr. Salette Dreyfus who was
the co-founder of WikiLeaks with Julian
she's serious about transparency okay
you've given me fantastic information
John great to talk to you again my
pleasure good to talk to you take care
of it bye-bye speaking of I
yes we Came we saw he died every nation
in every region now has a decision to
make decision you think I'm joking
predator drunks you will never see it
coming
[Music]
knocks down the big Canadian over